Finding Aid for Jacob M. Price papers, 1940-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jacob M. Price papers 1940-2007
Price, Jacob M.
(in 13 boxes)
8.5 linear feet
0187 Aa 2
History professor at the University of Michigan (1956-1990) specializing in the early modern Atlantic economy, particularly the trade of tobacco and sugar between Europe and North America in the 17th and 18th centuries. Price served with the Army Air Force in China during World War II and twice served as chairman of the history department. Collection includes letters written during his military service, extensive correspondence with colleagues and scholars, material on the Francis Lowenheim case involving access to research material, and Price's research files and index cards detailing his research into colonial American and British merchants.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The main collection was donated in August 2012 (Donor No. 8204 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Jacob Myron Price, a pioneer in quantitative methods of historical study, was born on November 8th, 1925, in Worcester, Massachusetts to Oscar and Agnes (Pike) Price. He entered Harvard in 1942 but joined the Air Force in 1944, working as a cryptographic technician then serving as a staff sergeant, and was sent to India until 1946. Following his service, he received his A.B., A.M., and Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1947, 1948, and 1954, respectively. He was also a member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1954, he taught at Smith College before coming to the University of Michigan as an instructor in 1956. He became assistant professor in 1958, associate professor in 1961, and professor in 1964. Price served on every major committee within the Department of History, and served twice as its chair (1971-72, 1979-84). Price received the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award in 1981 and was awarded Professor Emeritus status in 1991 after he retired in December 1990.
Price was known for his lectures on general European history, economic history, and modern British history. One of his early publications was Reading for Life: Developing the College Student's Lifetime Reading Interest (1959, reprinted in 1968). Nationally, he served on the board of editors of four scholarly journals and held a number of positions in the American Historical Association, including chairing the committee on quantitative data from 1967 to 1974 and co-editing Dimensions of the Past (1972). He also led the North American Conference on British Studies and its Midwest conference. He was a Fellow of the Royal Historical Society and of the British Academy and he was prominent in the Institute of Early American History and Culture at Williamsburg, and in the Economic History Association, which named him its president in 1987-88. He was also a Visiting Fellow at All Soul's College in Oxford.
He is best known for his work on trade between North America and Europe in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. His initial research concerned the Anglo-American development of the market for tobacco in Russia from 1676 to 1722. His interpretations, based on archival research in France, Britain, and the United States, made his publications landmarks in the understanding of capital formation, economic development, and the role of trade on the eve of the Industrial Revolution. His monumental study of the tobacco trade France and the Chesapeake (1973), was awarded both the University of Michigan Press Book Award and the Gilbert Chinard Prize of the Society for French Historical Studies. Later, he published the highly-influential Capital and Credit in British Overseas Trade (1980). He received fellowships from a variety of organizations, and was a corresponding member of the Massachusetts Historical Society and a fellow of the Royal Historical Society.
The Jacob Price collection Collection includes letters written during his military service, extensive correspondence with colleagues and scholars, material on the Francis Lowenheim case involving access to research material, and Price's research files and index cards detailing his research into colonial American and British merchants. The Collection is organized into six series: Correspondence, Dictionary of National Biography, Lowenheim Case, Personal, Research, and Index Cards.
Subjects:
Atlantic Ocean Region--Commerce--Great Britain--History.; Capital--Great Britain--History.; International economic relations--Great Britain--America.; Great Britain--Economic conditions--17th century.; Great Britain--Economic conditions--18th century.; Merchant marine--Great Britain--History.; Tobacco industry--Great Britain.; University of Michigan. Department of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Price, Jacob M.; United States. Army Air Forces.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (5.2 linear feet) contains correspondence written to Jacob Price, covering a variety of topics and from a variety of people. The original alphabetical filing order has been kept. Of particular note is the correspondence that Price wrote to his family while he was serving in the Air Force during World War II, letters from universities offering him positions, queries sent to Price regarding his research, and correspondence with various academic publishers.
  - Ad Hoc Committee 1959-1990 (Box 1)
  - Air Force Service 1944-1946, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Albion 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Boyd 1952-1977 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Henry 1959 (Box 1)
  - American Antiquarian Society 1991, 1998, 2001 (Box 1)
  - American Historical Review 1966, 1984, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Archives 2001 (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society 1956, 1960-1961, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Youth Chorale 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Answers to Queries (By Country) 1952-1967 (Box 1)
  - Answers to Queries (By State and City) 1951-1987 (Box 1)
  - Answers to Queries (UK -- By Family) 1950-1980 (Box 1)
  - Answers to Queries (UK -- By Town) 1950-1973 (Box 1)
  - Arents Collection 1969, 1971, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Auster 1982, 1994 (Box 1)
  - A -- General (Box 1)
  - Bailyn, Bernard 1961-1997 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, J.W. 1961-2001 (Box 1)
  - Barker, Theo 1963-1992 (Box 1)
  - Barnes, Thomas 1960-1980 (Box 1)
  - Baxter, Steve 1976-1983 (Box 1)
  - Bertram, Paul 1958 (Box 1)
  - Beth Emeth (Temple) 2004 (Box 1)
  - Beth Israel Hospital 2000-2004 (Box 1)
  - Bien, Matthew 1969-1999 (Box 1)
  - Blacher, Harvey 1999 (Box 1)
  - Breslaw, Elaine 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Brenner, Robert 1972-1997 (Box 1)
  - Briere, Jean-François 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - British Academy 1992-2005 (Box 1)
  - British Airways 2000 (Box 1)
  - Bromley, Jack 1960-1985 (Box 1)
  - Brunsman, Denver 2000 (Box 1)
  - Business Historical Review 1962, 1984, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Butel, Paul 1977-1987 (Box 1)
  - B -- General, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cambridge University 1956-1969 (Box 1)
  - Cambridge University Press 1972-2005 (Box 1)
  - Cambridge Group 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Carr, Lois 1981-2000 (Box 1)
  - Centenarian Studies (New England) 2000 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Paul 1973-1987, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Clements Library 1979-2005 (Box 2)
  - Clive, John 1962-1990 (Box 2)
  - Cole, Wayne 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Cosmos Club 2000-2007 (Box 2)
  - Cullen, Louis 1962-2000 (Box 2)
  - C -- General, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Davis, Ralph 1971, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Department of History (University of Michigan) 1957-1990 (Box 2)
  - Dunn, Richard 1957-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - D -- General (Box 2)
  - Economic History Review and Society 1971-2004 (Box 2)
  - Elgar, Edward Publishing 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Etsweiler, John 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - Executors 1992, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Explorations in Economic History 1979 (Box 2)
  - E -- General (Box 2)
  - Flint (University of Michigan) 1995 (Box 2)
  - Fulbright Act 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - F -- General (Box 2)
  - Galenson, David 1978-1996 (Box 2)
  - Gibson, Charles 1972-1983 (Box 2)
  - Grassby, Richard 1973-1999 (Box 2)
  - G -- General (Box 2)
  - Hambledon Press 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Hammersley, George 1984-1987 (Box 2)
  - Hancock, David 1986-1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Harper, Lawrence 1955-1974 (Box 3)
  - Harvard Summer School 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Hemphill, John 1956-1989 (Box 3)
  - Historical Statistics of the United States 1996-2000 (Box 3)
  - History of Parliament 2005 (Box 3)
  - Hoechstelter, Adelheid 1987-1999 (Box 3)
  - H -- General, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - ING Barings 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - I -- General (Box 3)
  - Jones, Michael 2002 (Box 3)
  - Journal of American History 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  - Journal of British Studies 1979-1989 (Box 3)
  - Journal of Economic History 1967-1988 (Box 3)
  - Journal of Interdisciplinary History 1975-2002 (Box 3)
  - Journal of Modern History 1967-1971 (Box 3)
  - Journal of Southern History 1991 (Box 3)
  - J -- General, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Kahan, Arcadius 1981 (Box 3)
  - Kress Library of Business and Economics 1961-1979 (Box 3)
  - K -- General, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Landes, David 1956-1990 (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress 1964-1969 (Box 3)
  - Lindert, Peter 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Loades, David 1998 (Box 3)
  - London Flat 1991-2000 (Box 3)
  - Louis, Roger (University of Texas) 1997-1999 (Box 3)
  - L -- General (Box 3)
  - McClelland, Peter 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - McCusker, John 1975-1981, 2000-2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - McCusker-Morgan Project 1982-2000 (Box 4)
  - Mc -- General (Box 4)
  - MacMillan Reference 2005 (Box 4)
  - Malone, Joseph 1962, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society 1982 (Box 4)
  - Mathias, Peter 1978-2000 (Box 4)
  - Milken, Michael 1993, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Conference on British Studies 1997-2000 (Box 4)
  - M -- General, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Northwest Airlines (Box 4)
  - National Association of Scholars 1999, 2003 (Box 4)
  - N -- General (Box 4)
  - Owen, David 1963-1968 (Box 4)
  - Oxford and Cambridge University Club 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - O -- General (Box 4)
  - Pamphlet Publications (New Excise Project) 1983-1987 (Box 4)
  - Papers of George Washington 1977-2005 (Box 4)
  - Payment and Credit (Box 4)
  - Perspectives in American History 1982 (Box 4)
  - Pike Family 2004 (Box 4)
  - Police 1986-1998 (Box 4)
  - Position Offers 1953-1986 (Box 4)
  - Post Office 1993-1999 (Box 4)
  - Price-Currents 1966-1994 (Box 4)
  - Price, Malcolm 1981-1992 (Box 4)
  - Professional Correspondence 1956-2006 (Box 4)
  - P -- General, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Queries, Incoming 1953-1967 (Box 4)
  - Quinn, Dand 1982, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Rischin, Moses 1957-2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Ritchie, Roy 1974-1999 (Box 4)
  - Riverside Park Place 2003 (Box 4)
  - Roberts, Clayton 1986-2003 (Box 4)
  - Rockman, Bob 1957-2000 (Box 4)
  - Roessner, Philipp 2004 (Box 5)
  - Rosenthal, Julius and David 1942 (Box 5)
  - Roseveare, Henry 1992-2000 (Box 5)
  - Royal Historical Society 1990-2001 (Box 5)
  - Royster, Charles 1993 (Box 5)
  - R -- General (Box 5)
  - Sack, James 1984 (Box 5)
  - Shy, John 1969-1999 (Box 5)
  - Smout, Christopher 1963-1987 (Box 5)
  - Soloway, Dick 1960-2006 (Box 5)
  - Sperling, John 1958-1996 (Box 5)
  - S-So -- General, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Sp-St -- General, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Titcomb, Caldwell 1965-2006, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Triad Management 1998 (Box 5)
  - T -- General (Box 5)
  - University Hospital 1981 (Box 5)
  - Vann, James 1972-1985 (Box 5)
  - V -- General (Box 5)
  - Walcott, Robert 1954-1966 (Box 6)
  - Walton, Gary 1966-1976 (Box 6)
  - Who's Who in America 1976, 1984 (Box 6)
  - William and Mary Quarterly 1953-2003, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - W -- General, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Yamey, Basil 1989 (Box 6)
  - Y -- General 1978-1980 (Box 6)
  - Zaheclieh, Nuala 1986 (Box 6)
- Dictionary of National Biography
  The Dictionary of National Biography series (0.3 linear feet) contains the entries Price developed and submitted to be published in the Dictionary of National Biography on 18th century merchants involved in Anglo American trade. The files are organized alphabetically.
  - Fludyer, Samuel 1994 (Box 6)
  - Fordyce, Alexander 1994 (Box 6)
  - Haistwell, Edward 1995, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Hanbury, John 1997-1999 (Box 6)
  - Heathcote, Gilbert 1994 (Box 6)
  - Holden, Samuel 1997 (Box 6)
  - Jeffreys, Jeffrey 1997 (Box 6)
  - Jeffreys, John 1995 (Box 6)
  - Johnson, Joshua 1996-1998 (Box 6)
  - Lare, Thomas (Box 6)
- Lowenheim Case
  The Lowenheim Case series (0.2 linear feet) contains correspondence and reports relating to Price's friendship with historian Francis Lowenheim. The reports also show Price's support of Lowenheim in his dispute with the Roosevelt Library, the National Archives, and Harvard University Press and in his claim that documents needed in his research had been withheld from him.
  - 1969 (Box 6)
  - 1970 (Box 6)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Final Report (Box 6)
- Personal
  The Personal series (0.3 linear feet) contains photographs, Price's personal diary from 1940, two awards, points from his will, records from his time as a faculty member at the University of Michigan, and various copies of his curriculum vitae.
  - Curriculum Vitae 1989-2004 (Box 6)
  - Diary 1940 (Box 6)
  - Distinguished Faculty Award 1981 (Box 6)
  - Faculty Records 1959-1976 (Box 6)
  - Photo Album (Box 6)
  - Points for Will 1980 (Box 6)
  - University Press Book Award 1974 (Box 6)
- Research
  The Research series (0.4 linear feet) contains reports from Price's various research projects. Also included are copies of reviews of Price's books and a copy of Price's paper Merchants and Planters: The Market Structure of the Colonial Chesapeake Reconsidered, which he wrote for the Conference on Activism, Rhetoric, and Research (CARR).
  - Book Reviews 1960-1999 (Box 7)
  - Conference on Activism, Rhetoric, and Research Paper (Box 7)
  - Dimensions of the Past Book Reviews, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
  - "The Excise Affair Revisited" (Box 7)
  - Journal of a Research Project 1953 (Box 7)
  - Liverpool Biographical Sketches 1987 (Box 7)
  - Research Plans 1957, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - Tobacco Trade Research (Box 7)
  - Whitehaven-Lowther Research 1950-1965 (Box 7)
- Index Cards
  The Index Cards series (2 linear feet) is comprised of multiple boxes of index cards that Price wrote during his research. The boxes contain information on merchants, primarily organized alphabetically or geographically, that were of specific importance to Price's research into sugar or tobacco traders between America and the United Kingdom. The cards vary in degree of detail. Some contain biographical notes about the individual merchants, including their location and trade. Others contain information from other archival sources that have been compiled on the note cards.
  The index cards, when taken together, provide a unique alphabetical directory of British and British American merchants trading to and from Britain and her American colonies during the 17th and 18th century. They also form a unique concordance to thousands of archival and printed sources documenting the lives and labors of these entrepreneurs. They would be of particular interest to scholars of business and economic history of the English-speaking Atlantic area.
  - Sugar Imports, by merchant. London and Bristol 1719-1789 (Box 8)
  - Merchants, by name. Mostly London 1676-1719 (Box 9)
  - Merchants, by name. Bristol and Liverpool 1680-1723 (Box 10)
  - Merchants, by name, with date, location, trade, and references (Box 11)
  - Merchants, by name, with archival sources (Box 12)
  - Merchants, by name, with archival sources (Box 13)
    (continued)